<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
	<public>
		<program name="Hero Lab" url="https://www.wolflair.com">
			<programinfo>Hero Lab and the Hero Lab logo are Registered Trademarks of LWD Technology, Inc. Free download at https://www.wolflair.com
Pathfinder® and associated marks and logos are trademarks of Paizo Inc.®, and are used under license.</programinfo>
			<version version="8.6b" primary="8" secondary="6" tertiary="b" build="797"/>
		</program>
		<localization language="eng" units="imperial"/>
		<character active="yes" characterindex="1" nature="normal" role="pc" relationship="ally" type="Hero" name="Mark" playername="">
			<race racetext="human" name="human" ethnicity=""/>
			<alignment name="Chaotic Good"/>
			<templates summary=""/>
			<size name="Medium">
				<space text="5'" value="5"/>
				<reach text="5'" value="5"/>
			</size>
			<deity name="Desna"/>
			<challengerating value="4" text="CR 4"/>
			<xpaward value="1200" text="1,200 XP"/>
			<classes level="5" summary="summoner (synthesist) 5" summaryabbr="Sum 5">
				<class name="Summoner (Synthesist)" level="5" spells="Spontaneous" casterlevel="5" concentrationcheck="+10" overcomespellresistance="+5" basespelldc="15" castersource="Arcane">
					<arcanespellfailure text="0%" value="0"/>
				</class>
			</classes>
			<factions/>
			<types>
				<type name="Humanoid" active="yes"/>
			</types>
			<subtypes>
				<subtype name="Human"/>
			</subtypes>
			<heropoints enabled="no" total="0"/>
			<senses>
				<special name="Darkvision (60 feet)" shortname="Darkvision 60 ft.">
					<description>A creature with darkvision can see in total darkness, usually to a range of 60 feet. Within this range the creature can see as clearly as a sighted creature could see in an area of bright light. Darkvision is black and white only but otherwise like normal sight.</description>
				</special>
			</senses>
			<auras/>
			<favoredclasses/>
			<health hitdice="5d8+10" hitpoints="41" damage="0" nonlethal="0" currenthp="41"/>
			<xp total="15000"/>
			<money total="148" pp="0" gp="148" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" valuables="0"/>
			<personal gender="Male" age="18" hair="" eyes="" skin="">
				<description/>
				<charheight text="5' 4&quot;" value="64"/>
				<charweight text="140 lb." value="140"/>
			</personal>
			<languages>
				<language name="Common" useradded="no"/>
				<language name="Daemonic"/>
				<language name="Infernal"/>
			</languages>
			<attributes>
				<attribute name="Strength">
					<attrvalue text="8/19" base="8" modified="19"/>
					<attrbonus text="-1/+4" base="-1" modified="+4"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
				<attribute name="Dexterity">
					<attrvalue text="8/16" base="8" modified="16"/>
					<attrbonus text="-1/+3" base="-1" modified="+3"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
				<attribute name="Constitution">
					<attrvalue text="11/13" base="11" modified="13"/>
					<attrbonus text="0/+1" base="+0" modified="+1"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
				<attribute name="Intelligence">
					<attrvalue text="13" base="13" modified="13"/>
					<attrbonus text="+1" base="+1" modified="+1"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
				<attribute name="Wisdom">
					<attrvalue text="15" base="15" modified="15"/>
					<attrbonus text="+2" base="+2" modified="+2"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
				<attribute name="Charisma">
					<attrvalue text="20" base="20" modified="20"/>
					<attrbonus text="+5" base="+5" modified="+5"/>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</attribute>
			</attributes>
			<saves>
				<save name="Fortitude Save" abbr="Fort" save="+4" base="+1" fromattr="+1" fromresist="" frommisc="+2">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</save>
				<save name="Reflex Save" abbr="Ref" save="+6" base="+1" fromattr="+3" fromresist="" frommisc="+2">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</save>
				<save name="Will Save" abbr="Will" save="+8" base="+4" fromattr="+2" fromresist="" frommisc="+2">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</save>
				<allsaves save="+0" base="" fromresist="" frommisc="">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</allsaves>
			</saves>
			<defensive>
				<special name="Evasion (Ex)" shortname="Evasion" type="Extraordinary Ability" sourcetext="Master">
					<description>If an animal companion is subjected to an attack that normally allows a Reflex saving throw for half damage, it takes no damage if it makes a successful saving throw.</description>
					<specsource>Master</specsource>
				</special>
			</defensive>
			<damagereduction/>
			<immunities/>
			<resistances>
				<special name="Energy Resistance, Fire (10)" shortname="fire 10">
					<description>You have the specified Energy Resistance against Fire attacks.</description>
				</special>
			</resistances>
			<weaknesses/>
			<armorclass ac="23" touch="13" flatfooted="20" fromarmor="" fromshield="+2" fromdexterity="+3" fromwisdom="" fromcharisma="" fromsize="" fromnatural="+8" fromdeflect="" fromdodge="" frommisc="">
				<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
			</armorclass>
			<penalties>
				<penalty name="Armor Check Penalty" text="0" value="0"/>
				<penalty name="Max Dex Bonus" text="99999" value="99999"/>
			</penalties>
			<maneuvers cmb="+6" cmd="21" cmdflatfooted="18">
				<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				<maneuvertype name="Awesome Blow" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Bull Rush" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Dirty Trick" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Disarm" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Drag" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Feint" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Grapple" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Overrun" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Pull" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Push" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Reposition" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Steal" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Sunder" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
				<maneuvertype name="Trip" bonus="0" cmb="+6" cmd="21">
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</maneuvertype>
			</maneuvers>
			<initiative total="+3" attrtext="+3" misctext="+0" attrname="Dexterity">
				<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
			</initiative>
			<movement>
				<speed text="40'" value="40"/>
				<basespeed text="40'" value="40"/>
			</movement>
			<encumbrance carried="19.96" encumstr="19" light="174" medium="349.5" heavy="525" level="Light Load"/>
			<skills>
				<skill name="Acrobatics" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="3" armorcheck="yes">
					<description>You can keep your balance while traversing narrow or treacherous surfaces. You can also dive, flip, jump, and roll to avoid attacks and overcome obstacles.

Check: You can use Acrobatics to move on narrow surfaces and uneven ground without falling. A successful check allows you to move at half speed across such surfaces - only one check is needed per round. Use the following table to determine the base DC, which is then modified by the Acrobatics skill modifiers noted on page 89. While you are using Acrobatics in this way, you are considered flat-footed and lose your Dexterity bonus to your AC (if any). If you take damage while using Acrobatics, you must immediately make another Acrobatics check at the same DC to avoid falling or being knocked prone.

Surface Width: Base Acrobatics DC
Greater than 3 feet wide: 0*
1-3 feet wide: 5*
7-11 inches wide: 10
2-6 inches wide 15
Less than 2 inches wide: 20
* No Acrobatics check is needed to move across these surfaces unless the modifiers to the surface (see page 89) increase the DC to 10 or higher.

In addition, you can move through a threatened square without provoking an attack of opportunity from an enemy by using Acrobatics. When moving in this way, you move at half speed. You can move at full speed by increasing the DC of the check by 10. You cannot use Acrobatics to move past foes if your speed is reduced due to carrying a medium or heavy load or wearing medium or heavy armor. If an ability allows you to move at full speed under such conditions, you can use Acrobatics to move past foes. You can use Acrobatics in this way while prone, but doing so requires a full-round action to move 5 feet, and the DC is increased by 5. If you attempt to move through an enemy's space and fail the check, you lose the move action and provoke an attack of opportunity.

Situation: Base Acrobatics DC*
Move through a threatened area: Opponent's Combat Maneuver Defense
Move through an enemy's space: 5 + opponent's Combat Maneuver Defense
* This DC is used to avoid an attack of opportunity due to movement. This DC increases by 2 for each additional opponent avoided in 1 round.

Finally, you can use the Acrobatics skill to make jumps or to soften a fall. The base DC to make a jump is equal to the distance to be crossed (if horizontal) or four times the height to be reached (if vertical). These DCs double if you do not have at least 10 feet of space to get a running start. The only Acrobatics modifiers that apply are those concerning the surface you are jumping from. If you fail this check by 4 or less, you can attempt a DC 20 Reflex save to grab hold of the other side after having missed the jump. If you fail by 5 or more, you fail to make the jump and fall (or land prone, in the case of a vertical jump). Creatures with a base land speed above 30 feet receive a +4 racial bonus on Acrobatics checks made to jump for every 10 feet of their speed above 30 feet. Creatures with a base land speed below 30 feet receive a -4 racial bonus on Acrobatics checks made to jump for every 10 feet of their speed below 30 feet. No jump can allow you to exceed your maximum movement for the round. For a running jump, the result of your Acrobatics check indicates the distance traveled in the jump (and if the check fails, the distance at which you actually land and fall prone). Halve this result for a standing long jump to determine where you land.

When you deliberately fall any distance, even as a result of a missed jump, a DC 15 Acrobatics skill check allows you to ignore the first 10 feet fallen, although you still end up prone if you take damage from a fall. See the falling rules on page 443 for further details.

Long Jump: Acrobatics DC
5 feet: 5
10 feet: 10
15 feet: 15
20 feet: 20
Greater than 20 feet: +5 per 5 feet.

High Jump: Acrobatics DC
1 foot: 4
2 feet: 8
3 feet: 12
4 feet: 16
Greater than 4 feet: +4 per foot

Many conditions can affect your chances of success with Acrobatics checks. The following modifiers to target DCs apply to all Acrobatics skill checks. The modifiers stack with one another, but only the most severe modifier for any one condition applies.

Acrobatics Modifiers: DC Modifier
Slightly obstructed (gravel, sand): +2
Severely obstructed (cavern, rubble): +5
Slightly slippery (wet): +2
Severely slippery (icy): +5
Slightly sloped (less than 45°): +2
Severely sloped (greater than 45°): +5
Slightly unsteady (boat in rough water): +2
Moderately unsteady (boat in a storm): +5
Severely unsteady (earthquake): +10
Move at full speed on narrow or uneven surfaces: +5*
* This does not apply to checks made to jump.

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 87</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text="Speed greater/less than 30 ft.: +4 to jump">
						<situationalmodifier text="+4 to jump" source="Speed greater/less than 30 ft."/>
					</situationalmodifiers>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Appraise" ranks="0" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="1">
					<description>You can evaluate the monetary value of an object.

Check: A DC 20 Appraise check determines the value of a common item. If you succeed by 5 or more, you also determine if the item has magic properties, although this success does not grant knowledge of the magic item's abilities. If your fail the check by less than 5, you determine the price of that item to within 20% of its actual value. If you fail this check by 5 or more, the price is wildly inaccurate, subject to GM discretion. Particularly rare or exotic items might increase the DC of this check by 5 or more.

You can also use this check to determine the most valuable item visible in a treasure hoard. The DC of this check is generally 20 but can increase to as high as 30 for a particularly large hoard.

Action: Appraising an item takes 1 standard action. Determining the most valuable object in a treasure hoard takes 1 full-round action.

Try Again: Additional attempts to Appraise an item reveal the same result.

Special: A spellcaster with a raven familiar gains a +3 bonus on Appraise checks.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Bluff" ranks="2" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="7">
					<description>You know how to tell a lie.

Check: Bluff is an opposed skill check against your opponent's Sense Motive skill. If you use Bluff to fool someone, with a successful check you convince your opponent that what you are saying is true. Bluff checks are modified depending upon the believability of the lie. The following modifiers are applied to the roll of the creature attempting to tell the lie. Note that some lies are so improbable that it is impossible to convince anyone that they are true (subject to GM discretion).

Circumstances: Bluff Modifier
The target wants to believe you: +5
The lie is believable: +0
The lie is unlikely: -5
The lie is far-fetched: -10
The lie is impossible: -20
The target is drunk or impaired: +5
You possess convincing proof: up to +10

Feint: You can use Bluff to feint in combat, causing your opponent to be denied his Dexterity bonus to his AC against your next attack. The DC of this check is equal to 10 + your opponent's base attack bonus + your opponent's Wisdom modifier. If your opponent is trained in Sense Motive, the DC is instead equal to 10 + your opponent's Sense Motive bonus, if higher. For more information on feinting in combat, see Chapter 8.

Secret Messages: You can use Bluff to pass hidden messages along to another character without others understanding your true meaning by using innuendo to cloak your actual message. The DC of this check is 15 for simple messages and 20 for complex messages. If you are successful, the target automatically understands you, assuming you are communicating in a language that it understands. If your check fails by 5 or more, you deliver the wrong message. Other creatures that receive the message can decipher it by succeeding at an opposed Sense Motive check against your Bluff result.

Action: Attempting to deceive someone takes at least 1 round, but can possibly take longer if the lie is elaborate (as determined by the GM on a case-by-case basis).

Feinting in combat is a standard action. 

Using Bluff to deliver a secret message takes twice as long as the message would otherwise take to relay.

Try Again: If you fail to deceive someone, further attempts to deceive them are at a -10 penalty and may be impossible (GM discretion).

You can attempt to feint against someone again if you fail. Secret messages can be relayed again if the first attempt fails.

Special: A spellcaster with a viper familiar gains a +3 bonus on Bluff checks.

If you have the Deceitful feat, you get a bonus on Bluff checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Climb" ranks="0" attrbonus="4" attrname="STR" value="4" armorcheck="yes" tools="uses">
					<description>You are skilled at scaling vertical surfaces, from smooth city walls to rocky cliffs.

Check: With a successful Climb check, you can advance up, down, or across a slope, wall, or other steep incline (or even across a ceiling, provided it has handholds) at one-quarter your normal speed. A slope is considered to be any incline at an angle measuring less than 60 degrees; a wall is any incline at an angle measuring 60 degrees or more.

A Climb check that fails by 4 or less means that you make no progress, and one that fails by 5 or more means that you fall from whatever height you have already attained.

The DC of the check depends on the conditions of the climb. Compare the task with those on the following table to determine an appropriate DC.

Climb DC: Example Surface or Activity
0: A slope too steep to walk up, or a knotted rope with a wall to brace against.
5: A rope with a wall to brace against, or a knotted rope, or a rope affected by the rope trick spell.
10: A surface with ledges to hold on to and stand on, such as a very rough wall or a ship's rigging.
15: Any surface with adequate handholds and footholds (natural or artificial), such as a very rough natural rock surface or a tree, or an unknotted rope, or pulling yourself up when dangling by your hands.
20: An uneven surface with narrow handholds and footholds, such as a typical wall in a dungeon.
25: A rough surface, such as a natural rock wall or a brick wall.
30: An overhang or ceiling with handholds only.
 -: A perfectly smooth, flat vertical (or inverted) surface cannot be climbed.

Climb DC Modifier*: Example Surface or Activity
-10: Climbing a chimney (artificial or natural) or other location where you can brace against two opposite walls.
-5: Climbing a corner where you can brace against perpendicular walls.
+5: Surface is slippery.
* These modifiers are cumulative; use all that apply.

You need both hands free to climb, but you may cling to a wall with one hand while you cast a spell or take some other action that requires only one hand. While climbing, you can't move to avoid a blow, so you lose your Dexterity bonus to AC (if any). You also can't use a shield while climbing. Anytime you take damage while climbing, make a Climb check against the DC of the slope or wall. Failure means you fall from your current height and sustain the appropriate falling damage.

Accelerated Climbing: You try to climb more quickly than normal. By accepting a -5 penalty, you can move half your speed (instead of one-quarter your speed).

Make Your Own Handholds and Footholds: You can make your own handholds and footholds by pounding pitons into a wall. Doing so takes 1 minute per piton, and one piton is needed per 5 feet of distance. As with any surface that offers handholds and footholds, a wall with pitons in it has a DC of 15. In the same way, a climber with a handaxe or similar implement can cut handholds in an ice wall.

Catch Yourself When Falling: It's practically impossible to catch yourself on a wall while falling, yet if you wish to attempt such a difficult task, you can make a Climb check (DC = wall's DC + 20) to do so. It's much easier to catch yourself on a slope (DC = slope's DC + 10).

Catch a Falling Character While Climbing: If someone climbing above you or adjacent to you falls, you can attempt to catch the falling character if he or she is within your reach. Doing so requires a successful melee touch attack against the falling character (though he or she can voluntarily forego any Dexterity bonus to AC if desired). If you hit, you must immediately attempt a Climb check (DC = wall's DC + 10). Success indicates that you catch the falling character, but his total weight, including equipment, cannot exceed your heavy load limit or you automatically fall. If you fail your Climb check by 4 or less, you fail to stop the character's fall but don't lose your grip on the wall. If you fail by 5 or more, you fail to stop the character's fall and begin falling as well.

Action: Climbing is part of movement, so it's generally part of a move action (and may be combined with other types of movement in a move action). Each move action that includes any climbing requires a separate Climb check. Catching yourself or another falling character doesn't take an action.

Special: You can use a rope to haul a character upward (or lower a character) through sheer strength. You can lift double your maximum load in this manner.

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 90</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Diplomacy" ranks="0" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="5">
					<description>You can use this skill to persuade others to agree with your arguments, to resolve differences, and to gather valuable information or rumors from people. This skill is also used to negotiate conflicts by using the proper etiquette and manners suitable to the problem.

Check: You can change the initial attitudes of nonplayer characters with a successful check. The DC of this check depends on the creature's starting attitude toward you, adjusted by its Charisma modifier. If you succeed, the character's attitude toward you is improved by one step. For every 5 by which your check result exceeds the DC, the character's attitude toward you increases by one additional step. A creature's attitude cannot be shifted more than two steps up in this way, although the GM can override this rule in some situations. If you fail the check by 4 or less, the character's attitude toward you is unchanged. If you fail by 5 or more, the character's attitude toward you is decreased by one step.

You cannot use Diplomacy against a creature that does not understand you or has an Intelligence of 3 or less. Diplomacy is generally ineffective in combat and against creatures that intend to harm you or your allies in the immediate future. Any attitude shift caused through Diplomacy generally lasts for 1d4 hours but can last much longer or shorter depending upon the situation (GM discretion).

Starting Attitude: Diplomacy DC
Hostile: 25 + creature's Cha modifier
Unfriendly: 20 + creature's Cha modifier
Indifferent: 15 + creature's Cha modifier
Friendly: 10 + creature's Cha modifier
Helpful: 0 + creature's Cha modifier

If a creature's attitude toward you is at least indifferent, you can make requests of the creature. This is an additional Diplomacy check, using the creature's current attitude to determine the base DC, with one of the following modifiers. Once a creature's attitude has shifted to helpful, the creature gives in to most requests without a check, unless the request is against its nature or puts it in serious peril. Some requests automatically fail if the request goes against the creature's values or its nature, subject to GM discretion.

Request: Diplomacy DC Modifier
Give simple advice or directions: -5
Give detailed advice: +0
Give simple aid: +0
Reveal an unimportant secret: +5
Give lengthy or complicated aid: +5
Give dangerous aid: +10
Reveal an important secret: +10 or more
Give aid that could result in punishment: +15 or more
Additional requests: +5 per request

Gather Information: You can also use Diplomacy to gather information about a specific topic or individual. To do this, you must spend at least 1d4 hours canvassing people at local taverns, markets, and gathering places. The DC of this check depends on the obscurity of the information sought, but for most commonly known facts or rumors it is 10. For obscure or secret knowledge, the DC might increase to 20 or higher. The GM might rule that some topics are simply unknown to common folk.

Action: Using Diplomacy to influence a creature's attitude takes 1 minute of continuous interaction. Making a request of a creature takes 1 or more rounds of interaction, depending upon the complexity of the request. Using Diplomacy to gather information takes 1d4 hours of work searching for rumors and informants.

Try Again: You cannot use Diplomacy to influence a given creature's attitude more than once in a 24-hour period. If a request is refused, the result does not change with additional checks, although other requests might be made. You can retry Diplomacy checks made to gather information.

Special: If you have the Persuasive feat, you gain a bonus on Diplomacy checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Disable Device" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="1" armorcheck="yes" trainedonly="yes" usable="no" tools="needs">
					<description>You are skilled at disarming traps and opening locks. In addition, this skill lets you sabotage simple mechanical devices, such as catapults, wagon wheels, and doors.

Check: When disarming a trap or other device, the Disable Device check is made secretly, so that you don't necessarily know whether you've succeeded.

The DC depends on how tricky the device is. If the check succeeds, you disable the device. If it fails by 4 or less, you have failed but can try again. If you fail by 5 or more, something goes wrong. If the device is a trap, you trigger it. If you're attempting some sort of sabotage, you think the device is disabled, but it still works normally.

You also can rig simple devices such as saddles or wagon wheels to work normally for a while and then fail or fall off some time later (usually after 1d4 rounds or minutes of use).

Device: Time: Disable Device DC*: Example
Simple: 1 round: 10: Jam a lock
Tricky: 1d4 rounds: 15: Sabotage a wagon wheel
Difficult: 2d4 rounds: 20: Disarm a trap, reset a trap
Extreme: 2d4 rounds: 25: Disarm a complex trap, cleverly sabotage a clockwork device
* If you attempt to leave behind no trace of your tampering, add 5 to the DC.

Open Locks: The DC for opening a lock depends on its quality. If you do not have a set of thieves' tools, these DCs increase by 10.

Lock Quality: Disable Device DC
Simple: 20
Average: 25
Good: 30
Superior: 40

Action: The amount of time needed to make a Disable Device check depends on the task, as noted above. Disabling a simple device takes 1 round and is a full-round action. A tricky or difficult device requires 1d4 or 2d4 rounds. Attempting to open a lock is a full-round action.

Try Again: Varies. You can retry checks made to disable traps if you miss the check by 4 or less. You can retry checks made to open locks.

Special: If you have the Deft Hands feat, you get a bonus on Disable Device checks (see Chapter 5).

A rogue who beats a trap's DC by 10 or more can study the trap, figure out how it works, and bypass it without disarming it. A rogue can rig a trap so her allies can bypass it as well.

Restriction: Characters with the trapfinding ability (like rogues) can disarm magic traps. A magic trap generally has a DC of 25 + the level of the spell used to create it.

The spells fire trap, glyph of warding, symbol, and teleportation circle also create traps that a rogue can disarm with a successful Disable Device check. Spike growth and spike stones, however, create magic hazards against which Disable Device checks do not succeed. See the individual spell descriptions for details.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Disguise" ranks="0" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="5" tools="uses">
					<description>You are skilled at changing your appearance.

Check: Your Disguise check result determines how good the disguise is, and it is opposed by others' Perception check results. If you don't draw any attention to yourself, others do not get to make Perception checks. If you come to the attention of people who are suspicious (such as a guard who is watching commoners walking through a city gate), it can be assumed that such observers are taking 10 on their Perception checks.

You get only one Disguise check per use of the skill, even if several people make Perception checks against it. The Disguise check is made secretly, so that you can't be sure how good the result is.

The effectiveness of your disguise depends on how much you're changing your appearance. Disguise can be used to make yourself appear like a creature that is one size category larger or smaller than your actual size. This does not change your actual size or reach, should you enter combat while wearing such a disguise.

Disguise: Check Modifier
Minor details only: +5
Disguised as different gender (1): -2
Disguised as different race (1): -2
Disguised as different age category (1) -2 (2)
Disguised as different size category (1) -10
(1) These modifiers are cumulative; use all that apply.
(2) Per step of difference between your actual age category and your disguised age category. The steps are: young (younger than adulthood), adulthood, middle age, old, and venerable.

If you are impersonating a particular individual, those who know what that person looks like get a bonus on their Perception checks according to the table below. Furthermore, they are automatically considered to be suspicious of you, so opposed checks are always called for.

Familiarity: Viewer's Perception Check Bonus
Recognizes on sight: +4
Friends or associates: +6
Close friends: +8
Intimate: +10

An individual makes a Perception check to see through your disguise immediately upon meeting you and again every hour thereafter. If you casually meet a large number of different creatures, each for a short time, check once per day or hour, using an average Perception modifier for the group.

Action: Creating a disguise requires 1d3 × 10 minutes of work. Using magic (such as the disguise self spell) reduces this action to the time required to cast the spell or trigger the effect.

Try Again: Yes. You may try to redo a failed disguise, but once others know that a disguise was attempted, they'll be more suspicious.

Special: Magic that alters your form, such as alter self, disguise self, polymorph, or shapechange, grants you a +10 bonus on Disguise checks (see the individual spell descriptions). Divination magic that allows people to see through illusions (such as true seeing) does not penetrate a mundane disguise, but it can negate the magical component of a magically enhanced one.

You must make a Disguise check when you cast a simulacrum spell to determine how good the likeness is.

If you have the Deceitful feat, you gain a bonus on Disguise checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Escape Artist" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="3" armorcheck="yes">
					<description>Your training allows you to slip out of bonds and escape from grapples.

Check: The table below gives the DCs needed to escape various forms of restraints.
Ropes: The DC of your Escape Artist check is equal to the binder's Combat Maneuver Bonus +20.
Manacles and Masterwork Manacles: The DC for manacles is set by their construction (see the table below).
Tight Space: The DC noted is for getting through a space through which your head fits but your shoulders don't. If the space is long, you may need to make multiple checks. You can't squeeze through a space that your head does not fit through.
Grappler: You can make an Escape Artist check in place of a combat maneuver check to escape a grapple (see Chapter 8) or a pin.

Restraint: Escape Artist DC
Rope/bindings: Binder's CMB +20
Net, animate rope, command plants, control plants, or entangle: 20
Snare spell: 23
Manacles: 30
Tight space: 30
Masterwork manacles: 35
Grappler: Grappler's CMD

Action: Making an Escape Artist check to escape from rope bindings, manacles, or other restraints (except a grappler) requires 1 minute of work. Escaping from a net or an animate rope, command plants, control plants, or entangle spell is a full-round action. Escaping from a grapple or pin is a standard action. Squeezing through a tight space takes at least 1 minute, maybe longer, depending on how long the space is.

Try Again: Varies. You can make another check after a failed check if you're squeezing your way through a tight space, making multiple checks. If the situation permits, you can make additional checks, or even take 20, as long as you're not being actively opposed. If the DC to escape from rope or bindings is higher than 20 + your Escape Artist skill bonus, you cannot escape from the bonds using Escape Artist.

Special: If you have the Stealthy feat, you gain a bonus on Escape Artist checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Fly" ranks="2" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="8" armorcheck="yes" classskill="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at flying, through either the use of wings or magic, and can perform daring or complex maneuvers while airborne. Note that this skill does not give you the ability to fly.

Check: You generally need only make a Fly check when you are attempting a complex maneuver. Without making a check, a flying creature can remain flying at the end of its turn so long as it moves a distance greater than half its speed. It can also turn up to 45 degrees by sacrificing 5 feet of movement, can rise at half speed at an angle of 45 degrees, and can descend at any angle at normal speed. Note that these restrictions only apply to movement taken during your current turn. At the beginning of the next turn, you can move in a different direction than you did the previous turn without making a check. Taking any action that violates these rules requires a Fly check. The difficulty of these maneuvers varies depending upon the maneuver you are attempting, as noted on the following chart.

Flying Maneuver: Fly DC
Move less than half speed and remain flying: 10
Hover: 15
Turn greater than 45° by spending  5 feet of movement: 15
Turn 180° by spending 10 feet of movement: 20
Fly up at greater than 45° angle: 20

Attacked While Flying: You are not considered flat-footed while flying. If you are flying using wings and you take damage while flying, you must make a DC 10 Fly check to avoid losing 10 feet of altitude. This descent does not provoke an attack of opportunity and does not count against a creature's movement.

Collision While Flying: If you are using wings to fly and you collide with an object equal to your size or larger, you must immediately make a DC 25 Fly check to avoid plummeting to the ground, taking the appropriate falling damage.

Avoid Falling Damage: If you are falling and have the ability to fly, you can make a DC 10 Fly check to negate the damage. You cannot make this check if you are falling due to a failed Fly check or a collision.

High Wind Speeds: Flying in high winds adds penalties on your Fly checks as noted on Table 4-5. "Checked" means that creatures of that size or smaller must succeed on a DC 20 Fly check to move at all so long as the wind persists. "Blown away" means that creatures of that size or smaller must make a DC 25 Fly check or be blown back 2d6 × 10 feet and take 2d6 points of nonlethal damage. This check must be made every round the creature remains airborne. A creature that is blown away must still make a DC 20 Fly check to move due to also being checked.

Action: None. A Fly check doesn't require an action; it is made as part of another action or as a reaction to a situation.

Try Again: Varies. You can attempt a Fly check to perform the same maneuver on subsequent rounds. If you are using wings and you fail a Fly check by 5 or more, you plummet to the ground, taking the appropriate falling damage (see Chapter 13).

Special: A spellcaster with a bat familiar gains a +3 bonus on Fly checks.

Creatures with a fly speed treat the Fly skill as a class skill. A creature with a natural fly speed receives a bonus (or penalty) on Fly skill checks depending on its maneuverability: Clumsy -8, Poor -4, Average +0, Good +4, Perfect +8. Creatures without a listed maneuverability rating are assumed to have average maneuverability.

A creature larger or smaller than Medium takes a size bonus or penalty on Fly checks depending on its size category: Fine +8, Diminutive +6, Tiny +4, Small +2, Large -2, Huge -4, Gargantuan -6, Colossal -8.

You cannot take ranks in this skill without a natural means of flight or gliding. Creatures can also take ranks in Fly if they possess a reliable means of flying every day (either through a spell or other special ability).

If you have the Acrobatic feat, you get a bonus on Fly checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Handle Animal" ranks="0" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="5" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes" usable="no">
					<description>You are trained at working with animals, and can teach them tricks, get them to follow your simple commands, or even domesticate them.

Check: The DC depends on what you are trying to do.

Task: Handle Animal DC
Handle an animal: 10
"Push" an animal: 25
Teach an animal a trick: 15 or 20*
Train an animal for a general purpose: 15 or 20*
Rear a wild animal: 15 + HD of animal
* See the specific trick or purpose below.

Handle an Animal: This task involves commanding an animal to perform a task or trick that it knows. If the animal is wounded or has taken any nonlethal damage or ability score damage, the DC increases by 2. If your check succeeds, the animal performs the task or trick on its next action.

"Push" an Animal: To push an animal means to get it to perform a task or trick that it doesn't know but is physically capable of performing. This category also covers making an animal perform a forced march or forcing it to hustle for more than 1 hour between sleep cycles. If the animal is wounded or has taken any nonlethal damage or ability score damage, the DC increases by 2. If your check succeeds, the animal performs the task or trick on its next action.

Teach an Animal a Trick: You can teach an animal a specific trick with 1 week of work and a successful Handle Animal check against the indicated DC. An animal with an Intelligence score of 1 can learn a maximum of three tricks, while an animal with an Intelligence score of 2 can learn a maximum of six tricks. Possible tricks (and their associated DCs) include, but are not necessarily limited to, the following.
• Attack (DC 20): The animal attacks apparent enemies. You may point to a particular creature that you wish the animal to attack, and it will comply if able. Normally, an animal will attack only humanoids, monstrous humanoids, giants, or other animals. Teaching an animal to attack all creatures (including such unnatural creatures as undead and aberrations) counts as two tricks.
• Come (DC 15): The animal comes to you, even if it normally would not do so.
• Defend (DC 20): The animal defends you (or is ready to defend you if no threat is present), even without any command being given. Alternatively, you can command the animal to defend another specific character.
• Down (DC 15): The animal breaks off from combat or otherwise backs down. An animal that doesn't know this trick continues to fight until it must flee (due to injury, a fear effect, or the like) or its opponent is defeated.
• Fetch (DC 15): The animal goes and gets something. If you do not point out a specific item, the animal fetches a random object.
• Guard (DC 20): The animal stays in place and prevents others from approaching.
• Heel (DC 15): The animal follows you closely, even to places where it normally wouldn't go.
• Perform (DC 15): The animal performs a variety of simple tricks, such as sitting up, rolling over, roaring or barking, and so on.
• Seek (DC 15): The animal moves into an area and looks around for anything that is obviously alive or animate.
• Stay (DC 15): The animal stays in place, waiting for you to return. It does not challenge other creatures that come by, though it still defends itself if it needs to.
• Track (DC 20): The animal tracks the scent presented to it. (This requires the animal to have the scent ability.)
• Work (DC 15): The animal pulls or pushes a medium or heavy load.

Train an Animal for a General Purpose: Rather than teaching an animal individual tricks, you can simply train it for a general purpose. Essentially, an animal's purpose represents a preselected set of known tricks that fit into a common scheme, such as guarding or heavy labor. The animal must meet all the normal prerequisites for all tricks included in the training package. If the package includes more than three tricks, the animal must have an Intelligence score of 2 or higher.

An animal can be trained for only one general purpose, though if the creature is capable of learning additional tricks (above and beyond those included in its general purpose), it may do so. Training an animal for a purpose requires fewer checks than teaching individual tricks does, but no less time.
• Combat Training (DC 20): An animal trained to bear a rider into combat knows the tricks attack, come, defend, down, guard, and heel. Training an animal for combat riding takes 6 weeks. You may also "upgrade" an animal trained for riding to one trained for combat by spending 3 weeks and making a successful DC 20 Handle Animal check. The new general purpose and tricks completely replace the animal's previous purpose and any tricks it once knew. Many horses and riding dogs are trained in this way.

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 97.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Heal" ranks="0" attrbonus="2" attrname="WIS" value="2" tools="uses">
					<description>You are skilled at tending to wounds and ailments.

Check: The DC and effect of a Heal check depend on the task you attempt.

Task DC
First aid: 15
Long-term care: 15
Treat wounds from caltrops, spike growth, or spike stones: 15
Treat deadly wounds: 20
Treat poison: Poison's save DC
Treat disease: Disease's save DC

First Aid: You usually use first aid to save a dying character. If a character has negative hit points and is losing hit points (at the rate of 1 per round, 1 per hour, or 1 per day), you can make him stable. A stable character regains no hit points but stops losing them. First aid also stops a character from losing hit points due to effects that cause bleed (see Appendix 2 for rules on bleed damage).

Long-Term Care: Providing long-term care means treating a wounded person for a day or more. If your Heal check is successful, the patient recovers hit points or ability score points lost to ability damage at twice the normal rate: 2 hit points per level for a full 8 hours of rest in a day, or 4 hit points per level for each full day of complete rest; 2 ability score points for a full 8 hours of rest in a day, or 4 ability score points for each full day of complete rest.

You can tend to as many as six patients at a time. You need a few items and supplies (bandages, salves, and so on) that are easy to come by in settled lands. Giving long-term care counts as light activity for the healer. You cannot give long-term care to yourself.

Treat Wounds from Caltrops, Spike Growth, or Spike Stones: A creature wounded by stepping on a caltrop moves at half normal speed. A successful Heal check removes this movement penalty.

A creature wounded by a spike growth or spike stones spell must succeed on a Reflex save or take injuries that reduce his speed by one-third. Another character can remove this penalty by taking 10 minutes to dress the victim's injuries and succeeding on a Heal check against the spell's save DC.
Treat Deadly Wounds: When treating deadly wounds, you can restore hit points to a damaged creature.

Treating deadly wounds restores 1 hit point per level of the creature. If you exceed the DC by 5 or more, add your Wisdom modifier (if positive) to this amount. A creature can only benefit from its deadly wounds being treated within 24 hours of being injured and never more than once per day. You must expend two uses from a healer's kit to perform this task. You take a -2 penalty on your Heal skill check for each use from the healer's kit that you lack.

Treat Poison: To treat poison means to tend to a single character who has been poisoned and who is going to take more damage from the poison (or suffer some other effect). Every time the poisoned character makes a saving throw against the poison, you make a Heal check. If your Heal check exceeds the DC of the poison, the character receives a +4 competence bonus on his saving throw against the poison.

Treat Disease: To treat a disease means to tend to a single diseased character. Every time the diseased character makes a saving throw against disease effects, you make a Heal check. If your Heal check exceeds the DC of the disease, the character receives a +4 competence bonus on his saving throw against the disease.

Action: Providing first aid, treating a wound, or treating poison is a standard action. Treating a disease or tending a creature wounded by a spike growth or spike stones spell takes 10 minutes of work. Treating deadly wounds takes 1 hour of work. Providing long-term care requires 8 hours of light activity.

Try Again: Varies. Generally speaking, you can't try a Heal check again without witnessing proof of the original check's failure. You can always retry a check to provide first aid, assuming the target of the previous attempt is still alive.

Special: A character with the Self-Sufficient feat gets a bonus on Heal checks (see Chapter 5).

A healer's kit gives you a +2 circumstance bonus on Heal checks.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Intimidate" ranks="0" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="5">
					<description>You can use this skill to frighten your opponents or to get them to act in a way that benefits you. This skill includes verbal threats and displays of prowess.

Check: You can use Intimidate to force an opponent to act friendly toward you for 1d6 × 10 minutes with a successful check. The DC of this check is equal to 10 + the target's Hit Dice + the target's Wisdom modifier.

If successful, the target gives you the information you desire, takes actions that do not endanger it, or otherwise offers limited assistance. After the Intimidate expires, the target treats you as unfriendly and may report you to local authorities. If you fail this check by 5 or more, the target attempts to deceive you or otherwise hinder your activities.

Demoralize: You can use this skill to cause an opponent to become shaken for a number of rounds. The DC of this check is equal to 10 + the target's Hit Dice + the target's Wisdom modifier. If you are successful, the target is shaken for 1 round. This duration increases by 1 round for every 5 by which you beat the DC. You can only threaten an opponent this way if they are within 30 feet. Using demoralize on the same creature only extends the duration; it does not create a stronger fear condition.

Action: Using Intimidate to change an opponent's attitude requires 1 minute of conversation. Demoralizing an opponent is a standard action.

Try Again: You can attempt to Intimidate an opponent again, but each additional check increases the DC by +5. This increase resets after 1 hour has passed.

Special: You also gain a +4 bonus on Intimidate checks if you are larger than your target and a -4 penalty on Intimidate checks if you are smaller than your target.

If you have the Persuasive feat, you get a bonus on Intimidate checks (see Chapter 5).

A half-orc gets a +2 bonus on Intimidate checks.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Knowledge (arcana)" ranks="1" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="5" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are educated in a field of study and can answer both simple and complex questions. Like the Craft, Perform, and Profession skills, Knowledge actually encompasses a number of different specialties. Below are listed typical fields of study.

• Arcana (ancient mysteries, magic traditions, arcane symbols, constructs, dragons, magical beasts)
• Dungeoneering (aberrations, caverns, oozes, spelunking)
• Engineering (buildings, aqueducts, bridges, fortifications)
• Geography (lands, terrain, climate, people)
• History (wars, colonies, migrations, founding of cities)
• Local (legends, personalities, inhabitants, laws, customs, traditions, humanoids)
• Nature (animals, fey, monstrous humanoids, plants, seasons and cycles, weather, vermin)
• Nobility (lineages, heraldry, personalities, royalty)
• Planes (the Inner Planes, the Outer Planes, the Astral Plane, the Ethereal Plane, outsiders, planar magic)
• Religion (gods and goddesses, mythic history, ecclesiastic tradition, holy symbols, undead)

Check: Answering a question within your field of study has a DC of 10 (for really easy questions), 15 (for basic questions), or 20 to 30 (for really tough questions).

You can use this skill to identify monsters and their special powers or vulnerabilities. In general, the DC of such a check equals 10 + the monster's CR. For common monsters, such as goblins, the DC of this check equals 5 + the monster's CR. For particularly rare monsters, such as the tarrasque, the DC of this check equals 15 + the monster's CR, or more. A successful check allows you to remember a bit of useful information about that monster. For every 5 points by which your check result exceeds the DC, you recall another piece of useful information. Many of the Knowledge skills have specific uses as noted on Table 4-6.

Action: Usually none. In most cases, a Knowledge check doesn't take an action (but see "Untrained," below).

Try Again: No. The check represents what you know, and thinking about a topic a second time doesn't let you know something that you never learned in the first place.

Untrained: You cannot make an untrained Knowledge check with a DC higher than 10. If you have access to an extensive library that covers a specific skill, this limit is removed. The time to make checks using a library, however, increases to 1d4 hours. Particularly complete libraries might even grant a bonus on Knowledge checks in the fields that they cover.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Knowledge (local)" ranks="2" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="6" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are educated in a field of study and can answer both simple and complex questions. Like the Craft, Perform, and Profession skills, Knowledge actually encompasses a number of different specialties. Below are listed typical fields of study.

• Arcana (ancient mysteries, magic traditions, arcane symbols, constructs, dragons, magical beasts)
• Dungeoneering (aberrations, caverns, oozes, spelunking)
• Engineering (buildings, aqueducts, bridges, fortifications)
• Geography (lands, terrain, climate, people)
• History (wars, colonies, migrations, founding of cities)
• Local (legends, personalities, inhabitants, laws, customs, traditions, humanoids)
• Nature (animals, fey, monstrous humanoids, plants, seasons and cycles, weather, vermin)
• Nobility (lineages, heraldry, personalities, royalty)
• Planes (the Inner Planes, the Outer Planes, the Astral Plane, the Ethereal Plane, outsiders, planar magic)
• Religion (gods and goddesses, mythic history, ecclesiastic tradition, holy symbols, undead)

Check: Answering a question within your field of study has a DC of 10 (for really easy questions), 15 (for basic questions), or 20 to 30 (for really tough questions).

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 99.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Knowledge (planes)" ranks="2" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="6" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are educated in a field of study and can answer both simple and complex questions. Like the Craft, Perform, and Profession skills, Knowledge actually encompasses a number of different specialties. Below are listed typical fields of study.

• Arcana (ancient mysteries, magic traditions, arcane symbols, constructs, dragons, magical beasts)
• Dungeoneering (aberrations, caverns, oozes, spelunking)
• Engineering (buildings, aqueducts, bridges, fortifications)
• Geography (lands, terrain, climate, people)
• History (wars, colonies, migrations, founding of cities)
• Local (legends, personalities, inhabitants, laws, customs, traditions, humanoids)
• Nature (animals, fey, monstrous humanoids, plants, seasons and cycles, weather, vermin)
• Nobility (lineages, heraldry, personalities, royalty)
• Planes (the Inner Planes, the Outer Planes, the Astral Plane, the Ethereal Plane, outsiders, planar magic)
• Religion (gods and goddesses, mythic history, ecclesiastic tradition, holy symbols, undead)

Check: Answering a question within your field of study has a DC of 10 (for really easy questions), 15 (for basic questions), or 20 to 30 (for really tough questions).

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 99.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Linguistics" ranks="1" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="5" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at working with language, in both its spoken and written forms. You can speak multiple languages, and can decipher nearly any tongue given enough time. Your skill in writing allows you to create and detect forgeries as well.

Check: You can decipher writing in an unfamiliar language or a message written in an incomplete or archaic form. The base DC is 20 for the simplest messages, 25 for standard texts, and 30 or higher for intricate, exotic, or very old writing. If the check succeeds, you understand the general content of a piece of writing about one page long (or the equivalent). If the check fails, make a DC 5 Wisdom check to see if you avoid drawing a false conclusion about the text. (Success means that you do not draw a false conclusion; failure means that you do.)

Both the Linguistics check and (if necessary) the Wisdom check are made secretly by the GM, so that you can't tell whether the conclusion you draw is true or false.

Condition: Linguistics Check Modifier
Type of document unknown to reader: -2
Type of document somewhat known to reader: +0
Type of document well known to reader: +2
Handwriting not known to reader: -2
Handwriting somewhat known to reader: +0
Handwriting intimately known to reader: +2
Reader only casually reviews the document: -2
Document contradicts orders or knowledge: +2

Create or Detect Forgeries: Forgery requires writing materials appropriate to the document being forged. To forge a document on which the handwriting is not specific to a person, you need only to have seen a similar document before, and you gain a +8 bonus on your check. To forge a signature, you need an autograph of that person to copy, and you gain a +4 bonus on the check. To forge a longer document written in the hand of some particular person, a large sample of that person's handwriting is needed.

The Linguistics check is made secretly, so that you're not sure how good your forgery is. As with Disguise, you don't make a check until someone examines the work. Your Linguistics check is opposed by the Linguistics check of the person who examines the document to verify its authenticity. The examiner gains modifiers if any of the conditions are listed on the table found on the previous page.

Learn a Language: Whenever you put a rank into this skill, you learn to speak and read a new language. Common languages (and their typical speakers) include the following.
• Abyssal (demons and other chaotic evil outsiders)
• Aklo (derros, inhuman or otherworldly monsters, evil fey)
• Aquan (aquatic creatures, water-based creatures)
• Auran (flying creatures, air-based creatures)
• Celestial (angels and other good outsiders)
• Common (humans and the core races from Chapter 2)
• Draconic (dragons, reptilian humanoids)
• Druidic (druids only)
• Dwarven (dwarves)
• Elven (elves, half-elves)
• Giant (cyclopses, ettins, giants, ogres, trolls)
• Gnome (gnomes)
• Goblin (bugbears, goblins, hobgoblins)
• Gnoll (gnolls)
• Halfling (halflings)
• Ignan (fire-based creatures)
• Infernal (devils and other lawful evil outsiders)
• Orc (orcs, half-orcs)
• Sylvan (centaurs, fey creatures, plant creatures, unicorns)
• Terran (earth-based creatures)
• Undercommon (drow, duergar, morlocks, svirfneblin)

Action: Varies. Deciphering a page of ordinary text takes 1 minute (10 consecutive rounds). Creating a forgery can take anywhere from 1 minute to 1d4 minutes per page. Detecting a forgery using Linguistics takes 1 round of examination per page.

Try Again: Yes.

Special: You must be trained to use this skill, but you can always attempt to read archaic and strange forms of your own racial bonus languages. In addition, you can also always attempt to detect a forgery.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Perception" ranks="1" attrbonus="2" attrname="WIS" value="3">
					<description>Your senses allow you to notice fine details and alert you to danger. Perception covers all five senses, including sight, hearing, touch, taste, and smell.

Check: Perception has a number of uses, the most common of which is an opposed check versus an opponent's Stealth check to notice the opponent and avoid being surprised. If you are successful, you notice the opponent and can react accordingly. If you fail, your opponent can take a variety of actions, including sneaking past you and attacking you.

Perception is also used to notice fine details in the environment. The DC to notice such details varies depending upon distance, the environment, and how noticeable the detail is. The following table gives a number of guidelines.

Detail: Perception DC
Hear the sound of battle: -10
Notice the stench of rotting garbage: -10
Detect the smell of smoke: 0
Hear the details of a conversation: 0
Notice a visible creature: 0
Determine if food is spoiled: 5
Hear the sound of a creature walking: 10
Hear the details of a whispered conversation: 15
Find the average concealed door: 15
Hear the sound of a key being turned in a lock: 20
Find the average secret door: 20
Hear a bow being drawn: 25
Sense a burrowing creature underneath you: 25
Notice a pickpocket: Opposed by Sleight of Hand
Notice a creature using Stealth: Opposed by Stealth
Find a hidden trap: Varies by trap
Identify the powers of a potion through taste: 15 + the potion's caster level

Perception Modifiers: DC Modifier
Distance to the source, object, or creature: +1/10 feet
Through a closed door: +5
Through a wall: +10/foot of thickness
Favorable conditions (1): -2
Unfavorable conditions (1): +2
Terrible conditions (2): +5
Creature making the check is distracted: +5
Creature making the check is asleep: +10
Creature or object is invisible: +20
(1) Favorable and unfavorable conditions depend upon the sense being used to make the check. For example, bright light might increase the DC of checks involving sight, while torchlight or moonlight might give a penalty. Background noise might reduce a DC involving hearing, while competing odors might penalize any DC involving scent.
(2) As for unfavorable conditions, but more extreme. For example, candlelight for DCs involving sight, a roaring dragon for DCs involving hearing, and an overpowering stench covering the area for DCs involving scent.

Action: Most Perception checks are reactive, made in response to observable stimulus. Intentionally searching for stimulus is a move action.

Try Again: Yes. You can try to sense something you missed the first time, so long as the stimulus is still present.

Special: Elves, half-elves, gnomes, and halflings receive a +2 racial bonus on Perception checks. Creatures with the scent special quality have a +8 bonus on Perception checks made to detect a scent. Creatures with the tremorsense special quality have a +8 bonus on Perception checks against creatures touching the ground and automatically make any such checks within their range. For more on special qualities, see Appendix 1.

A spellcaster with a hawk or owl familiar gains a +3 bonus on Perception checks. If you have the Alertness feat, you get a bonus on Perception checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Ride" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="3" armorcheck="yes" classskill="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at riding mounts, usually a horse, but possibly something more exotic, like a griffon or pegasus. If you attempt to ride a creature that is ill suited as a mount, you take a -5 penalty on your Ride checks.

Check: Typical riding actions don't require checks. You can saddle, mount, ride, and dismount from a mount without a problem. The following tasks do require checks.

Task: Ride DC
Guide with knees: 5
Stay in saddle: 5
Fight with a combat-trained mount: 10
Cover: 15
Soft fall: 15
Leap: 15
Spur mount: 15
Control mount in battle: 20
Fast mount or dismount: 20

Guide with Knees: You can guide your mount with your knees so you can use both hands in combat. Make your Ride check at the start of your turn. If you fail, you can use only one hand this round because you need to use the other to control your mount. This does not take an action.

Stay in Saddle: You can react instantly to try to avoid falling when your mount rears or bolts unexpectedly or when you take damage. This usage does not take an action.

Fight with a Combat-Trained Mount: If you direct your wartrained mount to attack in battle, you can still make your own attack or attacks normally. This usage is a free action.

Cover: You can react instantly to drop down and hang alongside your mount, using it as cover. You can't attack or cast spells while using your mount as cover. If you fail your Ride check, you don't get the cover benefit. Using this option is an immediate action, but recovering from this position is a move action (no check required).

Soft Fall: You negate damage when you fall off a mount. If you fail the Ride check, you take 1d6 points of damage and are prone. This usage does not take an action.

Leap: You can get your mount to leap obstacles as part of its movement. If the Ride check to make the leap succeeds, make a check using your Ride modifier or the mount's jump modifier, whichever is lower, to see how far the creature can jump. If you fail your Ride check, you fall off the mount when it leaps and take the appropriate falling damage (at least 1d6 points). This usage does not take an action but is part of the mount's movement.

Spur Mount: You can spur your mount to greater speed with a move action. A successful Ride check increases the mount's speed by 10 feet for 1 round but deals 1d3 points of damage to the creature. You can use this ability every round, but the mount becomes fatigued after a number of rounds equal to its Constitution score. This ability cannot be used on a fatigued mount.

Control Mount in Battle: As a move action, you can attempt to control a light horse, pony, heavy horse, or other mount not trained for combat riding while in battle. If you fail the Ride check, you can do nothing else in that round. You do not need to roll for horses or ponies trained for combat.

Fast Mount or Dismount: You can attempt to mount or dismount from a mount of up to one size category larger than yourself as a free action, provided that you still have a move action available that round. If you fail the Ride check, mounting or dismounting is a move action. You can't use fast mount or dismount on a mount more than one size category larger than yourself.

Action: Varies. Mounting or dismounting normally is a move action. Other checks are a move action, a free action, or no action at all, as noted above.

Special: If you are riding bareback, you take a -5 penalty on Ride checks.

If you have the Animal Affinity feat, you get a bonus on Ride checks (see Chapter 5).

If you use a military saddle you get a +2 circumstance bonus on Ride checks related to staying in the saddle.

Ride is a prerequisite for Mounted Archery, Mounted Combat, Ride-By Attack, Spirited Charge, and Trample.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Sense Motive" ranks="0" attrbonus="2" attrname="WIS" value="2">
					<description>You are skilled at detecting falsehoods and true intentions.

Check: A successful check lets you avoid being bluffed (see the Bluff skill). You can also use this skill to determine when "something is up" (that is, something odd is going on) or to assess someone's trustworthiness.

Task: Sense Motive DC
Hunch: 20
Sense enchantment: 25 or 15
Discern secret message: Varies

Hunch: This use of the skill involves making a gut assessment of the social situation. You can get the feeling from another's behavior that something is wrong, such as when you're talking to an impostor. Alternatively, you can get the feeling that someone is trustworthy.

Sense Enchantment: You can tell that someone's behavior is being influenced by an enchantment effect even if that person isn't aware of it. The usual DC is 25, but if the target is dominated (see dominate person), the DC is only 15 because of the limited range of the target's activities.

Discern Secret Message: You may use Sense Motive to detect that a hidden message is being transmitted via the Bluff skill. In this case, your Sense Motive check is opposed by the Bluff check of the character transmitting the message. For each piece of information relating to the message that you are missing, you take a -2 penalty on your Sense Motive check. If you succeed by 4 or less, you know that something hidden is being communicated, but you can't learn anything specific about its content. If you beat the DC by 5 or more, you intercept and understand the message. If you fail by 4 or less, you don't detect any hidden communication. If you fail by 5 or more, you might infer false information.

Action: Trying to gain information with Sense Motive generally takes at least 1 minute, and you could spend a whole evening trying to get a sense of the people around you.

Try Again: No, though you may make a Sense Motive check for each Bluff check made against you.

Special: A ranger gains a bonus on Sense Motive checks when using this skill against a favored enemy.

If you have the Alertness feat, you get a bonus on Sense Motive checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Sleight of Hand" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="3" armorcheck="yes" trainedonly="yes" usable="no">
					<description>Your training allows you to pick pockets, draw hidden weapons, and take a variety of actions without being noticed.

Check: A DC 10 Sleight of Hand check lets you palm a coin-sized, unattended object. Performing a minor feat of legerdemain, such as making a coin disappear, also has a DC of 10 unless an observer is determined to note where the item went.

When you use this skill under close observation, your skill check is opposed by the observer's Perception check. The observer's success doesn't prevent you from performing the action, just from doing it unnoticed.

You can hide a small object (including a light weapon or an easily concealed ranged weapon, such as a dart, sling, or hand crossbow) on your body. Your Sleight of Hand check is opposed by the Perception check of anyone observing you or of anyone frisking you. In the latter case, the searcher gains a +4 bonus on the Perception check, since it's generally easier to find such an object than to hide it. A dagger is easier to hide than most light weapons, and grants you a +2 bonus on your Sleight of Hand check to conceal it. An extraordinarily small object, such as a coin, shuriken, or ring, grants you a +4 bonus on your Sleight of Hand check to conceal it, and heavy or baggy clothing (such as a cloak) grants you a +2 bonus on the check.

Drawing a hidden weapon is a standard action and doesn't provoke an attack of opportunity.

If you try to take something from a creature, you must make a DC 20 Sleight of Hand check. The opponent makes a Perception check to detect the attempt, opposed by the Sleight of Hand check result you achieved when you tried to grab the item. An opponent who succeeds on this check notices the attempt, regardless of whether you got the item. You cannot use this skill to take an object from another creature during combat if the creature is aware of your presence.

You can also use Sleight of Hand to entertain an audience as though you were using the Perform skill. In such a case, your "act" encompasses elements of legerdemain, juggling, and the like.

Sleight of Hand DC: Task
10: Palm a coin-sized object, make a coin disappear
20: Lift a small object from a person

Action: Any Sleight of Hand check is normally a standard action. However, you may perform a Sleight of Hand check as a move action by taking a -20 penalty on the check.

Try Again: Yes, but after an initial failure, a second Sleight of Hand attempt against the same target (or while you are being watched by the same observer who noticed your previous attempt) increases the DC for the task by 10.

Untrained: An untrained Sleight of Hand check is simply a Dexterity check. Without actual training, you can't succeed on any Sleight of Hand check with a DC higher than 10, except for hiding an object on your body.

Special: If you have the Deft Hands feat, you get a bonus on Sleight of Hand checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Spellcraft" ranks="4" attrbonus="1" attrname="INT" value="8" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at the art of casting spells, identifying magic items, crafting magic items, and identifying spells as they are being cast.

Check: Spellcraft is used whenever your knowledge and skill of the technical art of casting a spell or crafting a magic item comes into question. This skill is also used to identify the properties of magic items in your possession through the use of spells such as detect magic and identify. The DC of this check varies depending upon the task at hand.

Action: Identifying a spell as it is being cast requires no action, but you must be able to clearly see the spell as it is being cast, and this incurs the same penalties as a Perception skill check due to distance, poor conditions, and other factors. Learning a spell from a spellbook takes 1 hour per level of the spell (0-level spells take 30 minutes). Preparing a spell from a borrowed spellbook does not add any time to your spell preparation. Making a Spellcraft check to craft a magic item is made as part of the creation process. Attempting to ascertain the properties of a magic item takes 3 rounds per item to be identified and you must be able to thoroughly examine the object.

Retry: You cannot retry checks made to identify a spell. If you fail to learn a spell from a spellbook or scroll, you must wait at least 1 week before you can try again. If you fail to prepare a spell from a borrowed spellbook, you cannot try again until the next day. When using detect magic or identify to learn the properties of magic items, you can only attempt to ascertain the properties of an individual item once per day. Additional attempts reveal the same results.

Special: If you are a specialist wizard, you get a +2 bonus on Spellcraft checks made to identify, learn, and prepare spells from your chosen school. Similarly, you take a -5 penalty on similar checks made concerning spells from your opposition schools.

An elf gets a +2 racial bonus on Spellcraft checks to identify the properties of magic items.

If you have the Magical Aptitude feat, you gain a bonus on Spellcraft checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Stealth" ranks="0" attrbonus="3" attrname="DEX" value="3" armorcheck="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at avoiding detection, allowing you to slip past foes or strike from an unseen position. Creatures that fail to beat your Stealth check are not aware of you and treat you as if you had total concealment. This skill covers hiding and moving silently.

Check: Your Stealth check is opposed by the Perception check of anyone who might notice you. You can move up to half your normal speed and use Stealth at no penalty. When moving at a speed greater than half but less than your normal speed, you take a -5 penalty. It's impossible to use Stealth while attacking, running, or charging.

Creatures gain a bonus or penalty on Stealth checks based on their size: Fine +16, Diminutive +12, Tiny +8, Small +4, Medium +0, Large -4, Huge -8, Gargantuan -12, Colossal -16.

If people are observing you using any of their senses (but typically sight), you can't use Stealth. Against most creatures, finding cover or concealment allows you to use Stealth. If your observers are momentarily distracted (such as by a Bluff check), you can attempt to use Stealth. While the others turn their attention from you, you can attempt a Stealth check if you can get to an unobserved place of some kind. This check, however, is made at a -10 penalty because you have to move fast.

Breaking Stealth: When you start your turn using Stealth, you can leave cover or concealment and remain unobserved as long as you succeed at a Stealth check and end your turn in cover or concealment. Your Stealth immediately ends after you make an attack roll, whether or not the attack is successful (except when sniping as noted below).

Sniping: If you've already successfully used Stealth at least 10 feet from your target, you can make one ranged attack and then immediately use Stealth again. You take a -20 penalty on your Stealth check to maintain your obscured location.

Creating a Diversion to Hide: You can use Bluff to allow you to use Stealth. A successful Bluff check can give you the momentary diversion you need to attempt a Stealth check while people are aware of you.

Action: Usually none. Normally, you make a Stealth check as part of movement, so it doesn't take a separate action. However, using Stealth immediately after a ranged attack (see Sniping, above) is a move action.

Special: If you are invisible, you gain a +40 bonus on Stealth checks if you are immobile, or a +20 bonus on Stealth checks if you're moving.

If you have the Stealthy feat, you get a bonus on Stealth checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Survival" ranks="0" attrbonus="2" attrname="WIS" value="2">
					<description>You are skilled at surviving in the wild and at navigating in the wilderness. You also excel at following trails and tracks left by others.

Check: You can keep yourself and others safe and fed in the wild. The table below gives the DCs for various tasks that require Survival checks.

Survival DC: Task
10: Get along in the wild. Move up to half your overland speed while hunting and foraging (no food or water supplies needed). You can provide food and water for one other person for every 2 points by which your check result exceeds 10.
15: Gain a +2 bonus on all Fortitude saves against severe weather while moving up to half your overland speed, or gain a +4 bonus if you remain stationary. You may grant the same bonus to one other character for every 1 point by which your Survival check result exceeds 15.
15: Keep from getting lost or avoid natural hazards, such as quicksand.
15: Predict the weather up to 24 hours in advance. For every 5 points by which your Survival check result exceeds 15, you can predict the weather for one additional day in advance.

Follow Tracks: To find tracks or to follow them for 1 mile requires a successful Survival check. You must make another Survival check every time the tracks become difficult to follow. If you are not trained in this skill, you can make untrained checks to find tracks, but you can follow them only if the DC for the task is 10 or lower. Alternatively, you can use the Perception skill to find a footprint or similar sign of a creature's passage using the same DCs, but you can't use Perception to follow tracks, even if someone else has already found them.

You move at half your normal speed while following tracks (or at your normal speed with a -5 penalty on the check, or at up to twice your normal speed with a -20 penalty on the check). The DC depends on the surface and the prevailing conditions, as given on the table.

Surface: Survival DC
Very soft ground: 5
Soft ground: 10
Firm ground: 15
Hard ground: 20

Very Soft Ground: Any surface (fresh snow, thick dust, wet mud) that holds deep, clear impressions of footprints.

Soft Ground: Any surface soft enough to yield to pressure, but firmer than wet mud or fresh snow, in which a creature leaves frequent but shallow footprints.

Firm Ground: Most normal outdoor surfaces (such as lawns, fields, woods, and the like) or exceptionally soft or dirty indoor surfaces (thick rugs and very dirty or dusty floors). The creature might leave some traces (broken branches or tufts of hair), but it leaves only occasional or partial footprints.

Hard Ground: Any surface that doesn't hold footprints at all, such as bare rock or an indoor floor. Most streambeds fall into this category, since any footprints left behind are obscured or washed away. The creature leaves only traces (scuff marks or displaced pebbles).

Condition: Survival DC Modifier
Every three creatures in the group being tracked: -1
Size of creature or creatures being tracked: (1)
Fine: +8
Diminutive: +4
Tiny: +2
Small: +1
Medium: +0
Large: -1
Huge: -2
Gargantuan: -4
Colossal: -8
Every 24 hours since the trail was made: +1
Every hour of rain since the trail was made: +1
Fresh snow since the trail was made: +10
Poor visibility: (2)
Overcast or moonless night: +6
Moonlight: +3
Fog or precipitation: +3
Tracked party hides trail (and moves at half speed): +5
(1) For a group of mixed sizes, apply only the modifier for the largest size category.
(2) Apply only the largest modifier from this category.

Several modifiers may apply to the Survival check, as given on the table above.

Action: Varies. A single Survival check may represent activity over the course of hours or a full day. A Survival check made to find tracks is at least a full-round action, and it may take even longer.

Try Again: Varies. For getting along in the wild or for gaining the Fortitude save bonus noted in the first table on page 107, you make a Survival check once every 24 hours. The result of that check applies until the next check is made. To avoid getting lost or avoid natural hazards, you make a Survival check whenever the situation calls for one. Retries to avoid getting lost in a specific situation or to avoid a specific natural hazard are not allowed. For finding tracks, you can retry a failed check after 1 hour (outdoors) or 10 minutes (indoors) of searching.

Special: If you are trained in Survival, you can automatically determine where true north lies in relation to yourself.

A ranger gains a bonus on Survival checks when using this skill to find or follow the tracks of a favored enemy.

If you have the Self-Sufficient feat, you get a bonus on Survival checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Swim" ranks="0" attrbonus="4" attrname="STR" value="4" armorcheck="yes">
					<description>You know how to swim and can do so even in stormy water.

Check: Make a Swim check once per round while you are in the water. Success means you may swim at up to half your speed (as a full-round action) or at a quarter of your speed (as a move action). If you fail by 4 or less, you make no progress. If you fail by 5 or more, you go underwater.

If you are underwater, either because you failed a Swim check or because you are swimming underwater intentionally, you must hold your breath. You can hold your breath for a number of rounds equal to twice your Constitution score, but only if you do nothing other than take move actions or free actions. If you take a standard action or a full-round action (such as making an attack), the remainder of the duration for which you can hold your breath is reduced by 1 round. (Effectively, a character in combat can hold his breath only half as long as normal.) After that period of time, you must make a DC 10 Constitution check every round to continue holding your breath. Each round, the DC for that check increases by 1. If you fail the Constitution check, you begin to drown. The DC for the Swim check depends on the water, as given on the table below.

Water: Swim DC
Calm water: 10
Rough water: 15
Stormy water: 20 (*)
(*) You can't take 10 on a Swim check in stormy water, even if you aren't otherwise being threatened or distracted.

Each hour that you swim, you must make a DC 20 Swim check or take 1d6 points of nonlethal damage from fatigue.

Action: A successful Swim check allows you to swim a quarter of your speed as a move action or half your speed as a full-round action.

Special: A creature with a swim speed can move through water at its indicated speed without making Swim checks. It gains a +8 racial bonus on any Swim check to perform a special action or avoid a hazard. The creature can always choose to take 10 on a Swim check, even if distracted or endangered when swimming. Such a creature can use the run action while swimming, provided that it swims in a straight line.

If you have the Athletic feat, you get a bonus on Swim checks (see Chapter 5).</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
				<skill name="Use Magic Device" ranks="5" attrbonus="5" attrname="CHA" value="13" classskill="yes" trainedonly="yes">
					<description>You are skilled at activating magic items, even if you are not otherwise trained in their use.

Check: You can use this skill to read a spell or to activate a magic item. Use Magic Device lets you use a magic item as if you had the spell ability or class features of another class, as if you were a different race, or as if you were of a different alignment.

You make a Use Magic Device check each time you activate a device such as a wand. If you are using the check to emulate an alignment or some other quality in an ongoing manner, you need to make the relevant Use Magic Device check once per hour.

You must consciously choose which requirement to emulate. That is, you must know what you are trying to emulate when you make a Use Magic Device check for that purpose. The DCs for various tasks involving Use Magic Device checks are summarized on the table below.

Task: Use Magic Device DC
Activate blindly: 25
Decipher a written spell: 25 + spell level
Use a scroll: 20 + caster level
Use a wand: 20
Emulate a class feature: 20
Emulate an ability score: See text
Emulate a race: 25
Emulate an alignment: 30

Activate Blindly: Some magic items are activated by special words, thoughts, or actions. You can activate such an item as if you were using the activation word, thought, or action, even when you're not and even if you don't know it. You do have to perform some equivalent activity in order to make the check. That is, you must speak, wave the item around, or otherwise attempt to get it to activate. You get a +2 bonus on your Use Magic Device check if you've activated the item in question at least once before. If you fail by 9 or less, you can't activate the device. If you fail by 10 or more, you suffer a mishap. A mishap means that magical energy gets released but doesn't do what you wanted it to do. The default mishaps are that the item affects the wrong target or that uncontrolled magical energy is released, dealing 2d6 points of damage to you. This mishap is in addition to the chance for a mishap that you normally risk when you cast a spell from a scroll that you could not otherwise cast yourself.

Decipher a Written Spell: This usage works just like deciphering a written spell with the Spellcraft skill, except that the DC is 5 points higher. Deciphering a written spell requires 1 minute of concentration.

Emulate an Ability Score: To cast a spell from a scroll, you need a high score in the appropriate ability (Intelligence for wizard spells, Wisdom for divine spells, or Charisma for sorcerer or bard spells). Your effective ability score (appropriate to the class you're emulating when you try to cast the spell from the scroll) is your Use Magic Device check result minus 15. If you already have a high enough score in the appropriate ability, you don't need to make this check.

Emulate an Alignment: Some magic items have positive or negative effects based on the user's alignment. Use Magic Device lets you use these items as if you were of an alignment of your choice. You can emulate only one alignment at a time.

Emulate a Class Feature: Sometimes you need to use a class feature to activate a magic item. In this case, your effective level in the emulated class equals your Use Magic Device check result minus 20. This skill does not let you actually use the class feature of another class. It just lets you activate items as if you had that class feature. If the class whose feature you are emulating has an alignment requirement, you must meet it, either honestly or by emulating an appropriate alignment with a separate Use Magic Device check (see above).

Emulate a Race: Some magic items work only for members of certain races, or work better for members of those races. You can use such an item as if you were a member of a race of your choice. You can emulate only one race at a time.

Use a Scroll: Normally, to cast a spell from a scroll, you must have the scroll's spell on your class spell list. Use Magic Device allows you to use a scroll as if you had a particular spell on your class spell list. The DC is equal to 20 + the caster level of the spell you are trying to cast from the scroll. In addition, casting a spell from a scroll requires a minimum score (10 + spell level) in the appropriate ability. If you don't have a sufficient score in that ability, you must emulate the ability score with a separate Use Magic Device check.

This use of the skill also applies to other spell completion magic items.

Continued - Core Rulebook, pg. 108.</description>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</skill>
			</skills>
			<skillabilities/>
			<feats>
				<feat name="Arcane Strike" categorytext="Combat">
					<description>You draw upon your arcane power to enhance your weapons with magical energy.

Prerequisite: Ability to cast arcane spells.

Benefit: As a swift action, you can imbue your weapons with a fraction of your power. For 1 round, your weapons deal +1 damage and are treated as magic for the purpose of overcoming damage reduction. For every five caster levels you possess, this bonus increases by +1, to a maximum of +5 at 20th level.</description>
					<featcategory>Combat</featcategory>
				</feat>
				<feat name="Armor Proficiency (Light)" categorytext="Combat" profgroup="yes" useradded="no">
					<description>You are skilled at wearing light armor.

Benefit: When you wear a type of armor with which you are proficient, the armor check penalty for that armor applies only to Dexterity- and Strength-based skill checks.

Normal: A character who is wearing armor with which he is not proficient applies its armor check penalty to attack rolls and to all skill checks that involve moving.

Special: All characters except monks, sorcerers, and wizards automatically have Light Armor Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</description>
					<featcategory>Combat</featcategory>
				</feat>
				<feat name="Extra Evolution" categorytext="">
					<description>Your eidolon has more evolutions.

Prerequisite: Eidolon class feature.

Benefit: Your eidolon's evolution pool increases by 1.

Special: This feat can be taken once at 1st level, and again at 5th, 10th, 15th, and 20th.</description>
				</feat>
				<feat name="Extra Evolution" categorytext="">
					<description>Your eidolon has more evolutions.

Prerequisite: Eidolon class feature.

Benefit: Your eidolon's evolution pool increases by 1.

Special: This feat can be taken once at 1st level, and again at 5th, 10th, 15th, and 20th.</description>
				</feat>
				<feat name="Power Attack -2/+4" categorytext="Combat">
					<description>You can make exceptionally deadly melee attacks by sacrificing accuracy for strength.

Prerequisites: Str 13, base attack bonus +1.

Benefit: You can choose to take a –1 penalty on all melee attack rolls and combat maneuver checks to gain a +2 bonus on all melee damage rolls. This bonus to damage is increased by half (+50%) if you are making an attack with a two-handed weapon, a one handed weapon using two hands, or a primary natural weapon that adds 1-1/2 times your Strength modifier on damage rolls. This bonus to damage is halved (–50%) if you are making an attack with an off-hand weapon or secondary natural weapon. When your base attack bonus reaches +4, and every 4 points thereafter, the penalty increases by –1 and the bonus to damage increases by +2. You must choose to use this feat before making an attack roll, and its effects last until your next turn. The bonus damage does not apply to touch attacks or effects that do not deal hit point damage.</description>
					<featcategory>Combat</featcategory>
				</feat>
				<feat name="Simple Weapon Proficiency - All" categorytext="Combat" profgroup="yes" useradded="no">
					<description>You are trained in the use of basic weapons.

Benefit: You make attack rolls with simple weapons without penalty.

Normal: When using a weapon with which you are not proficient, you take a –4 penalty on attack rolls.

Special: All characters except for druids, monks, and wizards are automatically proficient with all simple weapons. They need not select this feat.</description>
					<featcategory>Combat</featcategory>
				</feat>
			</feats>
			<traits/>
			<flaws/>
			<skilltricks/>
			<animaltricks/>
			<attack attackbonus="+4" meleeattack="+8" rangedattack="+7" baseattack="+4">
				<special name="Energy Attacks (Cold) (Ex)" shortname="Energy Attacks (Cold)" type="Extraordinary Ability">
					<description>An eidolon’s attacks become charged with energy. Pick one energy type: acid, cold, electricity, or fire. All of the eidolon’s natural attacks deal 1d6 points of energy damage of the chosen type on a successful hit. The summoner must be at least 5th level before selecting this evolution.</description>
				</special>
				<special name="Pounce (Ex)" shortname="Pounce" type="Extraordinary Ability">
					<description>When a creature with this special attack makes a charge, it can make a full attack (including rake attacks if the creature also has the rake ability).</description>
				</special>
			</attack>
			<melee>
				<weapon name="+1 bite (Bite)" categorytext="Melee Weapon" typetext="B/P/S" attack="+7" crit="×2" damage="1d6+11 plus 1d6 cold" useradded="no">
					<description>A creature's natural Bite attack.</description>
					<wepcategory>Melee Weapon</wepcategory>
					<weptype>Bludgeoning</weptype>
					<weptype>Piercing</weptype>
					<weptype>Slashing</weptype>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</weapon>
				<weapon name="+1 gore (Gore)" categorytext="Melee Weapon" typetext="P" attack="+7" crit="×2" damage="1d6+11 plus 1d6 cold" useradded="no">
					<description>A creature's natural Gore attack.</description>
					<wepcategory>Melee Weapon</wepcategory>
					<weptype>Piercing</weptype>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</weapon>
				<weapon name="Dagger" categorytext="Melee Weapon, Thrown Weapon" typetext="P/S" attack="+6" crit="19-20/×2" damage="1d4+10" quantity="1">
					<rangedattack attack="+7" rangeinctext="10'" rangeincvalue="10'"/>
					<weight text="1 lb" value="1"/>
					<cost text="2 gp" value="2"/>
					<description>A dagger is a fighting knife. Its blade is usually less than 1 foot long, and can be curved or straight, with one edge or two. Dagger designs vary widely, and can have many different names (such as a thrusting dagger being called a "dirk"). You get a +2 bonus on Sleight of Hand skill checks made to conceal a dagger on your body.</description>
					<wepcategory>Melee Weapon</wepcategory>
					<wepcategory>Thrown Weapon</wepcategory>
					<weptype>Piercing</weptype>
					<weptype>Slashing</weptype>
					<situationalmodifiers text=""/>
				</weapon>
			</melee>
			<ranged/>
			<defenses>
				<armor name="Natural armor" ac="+2" equipped="yes" natural="yes" useradded="no" quantity="1">
					<weight text="" value="0"/>
					<cost text="" value="0"/>
					<description/>
					<itemslot>Armor</itemslot>
				</armor>
				<armor name="Quilted cloth armor" ac="+1" quantity="1">
					<weight text="15 lbs" value="15"/>
					<cost text="100 gp" value="100"/>
					<description>This enhanced form of padded armor has internal layers specifically designed to trap arrows, bolts, darts, shuriken, thrown daggers, and other small ranged piercing weapons. When these kinds of weapons strike you, they tend to become snagged in these layers and fail to harm you. Wearing quilted cloth armor gives you DR 3/— against attacks of this kind. The special layers of the armor have no effect on other kinds of weapons.</description>
					<itemslot>Armor</itemslot>
				</armor>
			</defenses>
			<magicitems>
				<item name="Amulet of mighty fists +1" quantity="1">
					<weight text="" value="0"/>
					<cost text="4,000 gp" value="4000"/>
					<description>This amulet grants an enhancement bonus of +1 on attack and damage rolls with unarmed attacks and natural weapons. The enhancement bonus from an amulet of mighty fists does allow natural attacks and unarmed strikes to bypass damage reduction if the enhancement bonus is at least +3 (as with other weapons, see page 562 of the Core Rulebook).

Construction
Requirements: Craft Wondrous Item, greater magic fang, creator’s caster level must be at least three times the amulet’s bonus; Cost 2,000 gp</description>
					<itemslot>Neck</itemslot>
				</item>
				<item name="Belt of giant strength +2" quantity="1">
					<weight text="1 lb" value="1"/>
					<cost text="4,000 gp" value="4000"/>
					<description>This belt is a thick leather affair, often decorated with huge metal buckles. The belt grants the wearer an enhancement bonus to Strength of +2. Treat this as a temporary ability bonus for the first 24 hours the belt is worn.

Construction
Requirements: Craft Wondrous Item, bull’s strength; Cost 2,000 gp</description>
					<itemslot>Belt</itemslot>
				</item>
				<item name="Potion of cure serious wounds" quantity="1">
					<weight text="" value="0"/>
					<cost text="750 gp" value="750"/>
					<description>Cures 3d8 damage +1/level (max +15).</description>
				</item>
				<item name="Potion of haste" quantity="1">
					<weight text="" value="0"/>
					<cost text="750 gp" value="750"/>
					<description>One creature/level moves faster, +1 on attack rolls, AC, and Reflex saves.</description>
				</item>
				<item name="Potion of heroism" quantity="1">
					<weight text="" value="0"/>
					<cost text="750 gp" value="750"/>
					<description>Gives +2 bonus on attack rolls, saves, skill checks.</description>
				</item>
			</magicitems>
			<gear>
				<item name="Dagger" quantity="1">
					<weight text="1 lb" value="1"/>
					<cost text="2 gp" value="2"/>
					<description>A dagger is a fighting knife. Its blade is usually less than 1 foot long, and can be curved or straight, with one edge or two. Dagger designs vary widely, and can have many different names (such as a thrusting dagger being called a "dirk"). You get a +2 bonus on Sleight of Hand skill checks made to conceal a dagger on your body.</description>
				</item>
				<item name="Quilted cloth armor" quantity="1">
					<weight text="15 lbs" value="15"/>
					<cost text="100 gp" value="100"/>
					<description>This enhanced form of padded armor has internal layers specifically designed to trap arrows, bolts, darts, shuriken, thrown daggers, and other small ranged piercing weapons. When these kinds of weapons strike you, they tend to become snagged in these layers and fail to harm you. Wearing quilted cloth armor gives you DR 3/— against attacks of this kind. The special layers of the armor have no effect on other kinds of weapons.</description>
					<itemslot>Armor</itemslot>
				</item>
			</gear>
			<spelllike>
				<special name="Summon Monster III (8/day) (Sp)" shortname="Summon Monster (8/day)" type="Spell-Like Ability" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>At 1st level, a summoner can cast summon monster I as a spell-like ability a number of times per day equal to 3 + his Charisma modifier. Drawing on this ability uses up the same power that the summoner uses to call his eidolon. As a result, he can use this ability only when his eidolon is not summoned. He can cast this spell as a standard action, and the creatures remain for 1 minute per level (instead of 1 round per level). At 3rd level, and every 2 levels thereafter, the power of this ability increases by 1 spell level, allowing him to summon more powerful creatures (to a maximum of summon monster IX at 17th level). At 19th level, this ability can be used as gate or summon monster IX. If used as gate, the summoner must pay any required material components. A summoner cannot have more than one summon monster or gate spell active in this way at one time. If this ability is used again, any existing summon monster or gate from this spell-like ability immediately ends. These summon spells are considered to be part of the summoner’s spell list for the purposes of spell trigger and spell completion items. In addition, the summoner can expend uses of this ability to fulfill the construction requirements of any magic item he creates, so long as he can use this ability to cast the required spell.</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
			</spelllike>
			<trackedresources>
				<trackedresource name="Dagger" text="0/1" used="0" left="1" min="0" max="1"/>
				<trackedresource name="Fused Eidolon (29/29 HP)" text="0/29" used="0" left="29" min="0" max="29"/>
				<trackedresource name="Potion of cure serious wounds" text="0/1" used="0" left="1" min="0" max="1"/>
				<trackedresource name="Potion of haste" text="0/1" used="0" left="1" min="0" max="1"/>
				<trackedresource name="Potion of heroism" text="0/1" used="0" left="1" min="0" max="1"/>
				<trackedresource name="Summon Monster III (8/day) (Sp)" text="0/8" used="0" left="8" min="0" max="8"/>
			</trackedresources>
			<otherspecials>
				<special name="Eidolon Link (Ex)" shortname="Eidolon Link" type="Extraordinary Ability" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>A summoner and his eidolon share a mental link that allows for communication across any distance (as long as they are on the same plane). This communication is a free action, allowing the summoner to give orders to his eidolon at any time. In addition, magic items interfere with the summoner's connection to his eidolon. As a result, the summoner and his eidolon share magic item slots. For example, if the summoner is wearing a ring, his eidolon can wear no more than one ring. In case of a conflict, the items worn by the summoner remain active, and those used by the eidolon become dormant. The eidolon must possess the appropriate appendages to utilize a magic item.</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
				<special name="Fused Eidolon (29/29 HP)" shortname="Fused Eidolon" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>A synthesist summons the essence of a powerful outsider to meld with his own being. The synthesist wears the eidolon like translucent, living armor. The eidolon mimics all of the synthesist's movements, and the synthesist perceives through the eidolon's senses and speaks through its voice, as the two are now one creature.

While fused with his eidolon, the synthesist uses the eidolon's physical ability scores (Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution), but retains his own mental ability scores (Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma). The synthesist gains the eidolon's hit points as temporary hit points. When these hit points reach 0, the eidolon is killed and sent back to its home plane. The synthesist uses the eidolon's base attack bonus, and gains the eidolon's armor and natural armor bonuses and modifiers to ability scores. The synthesist also gains access to the eidolon's special abilities and the eidolon's evolutions. The synthesist is still limited to the eidolon's maximum number of natural attacks. The eidolon has no skills or feats of its own. The eidolon must be at least the same size as the synthesist. The eidolon must have limbs for the synthesist to cast spells with somatic components. The eidolon's temporary hit points can be restored with the rejuvenate eidolon spell.

While fused, the synthesist loses the benefits of his armor. He counts both as his original type and as an outsider for any effect related to type, whichever is worse for the synthesist. Spells such as banishment or dismissal work normally on the eidolon, but the synthesist is unaffected. Neither the synthesist nor his eidolon can be targeted separately, as they are fused into one creature. The synthesist and eidolon cannot take separate actions. While fused with his eidolon, the synthesist can use all of his own abilities and gear, except for his armor. In all other cases, this ability functions as the summoner's normal eidolon ability (for example, the synthesist cannot use his summon monster ability while the eidolon is present). This ability replaces the class's eidolon ability, bond senses, and life bond.

Eidolon
Quadruped
CG Medium outsider
AC 16 (+6 natural)
hp 29 (4d10+4)
Str 17, Dex 16, Con 13, Int 7, Wis 10, Cha 11
Base Atk +1
Evolutions Bite, Energy Attacks, Gore, Improved Damage, Improved Natural Armor, Limbs (Legs), Limbs (Legs), Pounce, Rake, Resistance, Fire 10</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
				<special name="Fused Link (Su)" shortname="Fused Link" type="Supernatural Ability" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>Starting at 1st level, the synthesist forms a close bond with his eidolon. Whenever the temporary hit points from his eidolon would be reduced to 0, the summoner can, as a free action, sacrifice any number of his own hit points. Each hit point sacrificed this way prevents 1 point of damage done to the eidolon (thus preventing the loss of the summoner's temporary hit points), preventing the eidolon from being killed and sent back to its home plane. This ability replaces life link.</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
				<special name="Pounce (Ex)" shortname="Pounce" type="Extraordinary Ability">
					<description>An eidolon gains quick reflexes, allowing it to make a full attack after a charge. This evolution is only available to eidolons of the quadruped base form.</description>
				</special>
				<special name="Share Spells with Eidolon (Ex)" shortname="Share Spells with Eidolon" type="Extraordinary Ability" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>The summoner may cast a spell with a target of "You" on his eidolon (as a spell with a range of touch) instead of on himself. A summoner may cast spells on his eidolon even if the spells normally do not affect creatures of the eidolon's type (outsider). Spells cast in this way must come from the summoner spell list. This ability does not allow the eidolon to share abilities that are not spells, even if they function like spells.</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
				<special name="Shielded Meld (Ex)" shortname="Shielded Meld" type="Extraordinary Ability" sourcetext="Summoner">
					<description>At 4th level, whenever the synthesist is fused with his eidolon, he gains a +2 shield bonus to his Armor Class and a +2 circumstance bonus on his saving throws. This ability replaces shield ally.

At 12th level, whenever the synthesist is fused with his eidolon, he gains a +4 shield bonus to his Armor Class and a +4 circumstance bonus on his saving throws. This ability replaces greater shield ally.</description>
					<specsource>Summoner</specsource>
				</special>
			</otherspecials>
			<spellsknown>
				<spell name="Detect Magic" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="60 ft." target="" area="cone-shaped emanation" effect="" duration="concentration, up to 1 min./level (D)" save="none" resist="no" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic" schooltext="Divination" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="None" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>You detect magical auras. The amount of information revealed depends on how long you study a particular area or subject.

1st Round: Presence or absence of magical auras.
2nd Round: Number of different magical auras and the power of the most potent aura.
3rd Round: The strength and location of each aura. If the items or creatures bearing the auras are in line of sight, you can make Knowledge (arcana) skill checks to determine the school of magic involved in each. (Make one check per aura: DC 15 + spell level, or 15 + 1/2 caster level for a nonspell effect.) If the aura eminates from a magic item, you can attempt to identify its properties (see Spellcraft).

Magical areas, multiple types of magic, or strong local magical emanations may distort or conceal weaker auras.

Aura Strength: An aura's power depends on a spell's functioning spell level or an item's caster level; see the accompanying table. If an aura falls into more than one category, detect magic indicates the stronger of the two.

Lingering Aura: A magical aura lingers after its original source dissipates (in the case of a spell) or is destroyed (in the case of a magic item). If detect magic is cast and directed at such a location, the spell indicates an aura strength of dim (even weaker than a faint aura). How long the aura lingers at this dim level depends on its original power:

Original Strength - Duration of Lingering Aura
Faint - 1d6 rounds
Moderate - 1d6 minutes
Strong - 1d6 x 10 minutes
Overwhelming - 1d6 days

Outsiders and elementals are not magical in themselves, but if they are summoned, the conjuration spell registers. Each round, you can turn to detect magic in a new area. The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.

Detect magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Divination</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Enlarge Person" level="1" class="Summoner" casttime="1 round" range="close (25 + 5 ft./2 levels)" target="one humanoid creature" area="" effect="" duration="1 min./level (D)" save="DC 16 Fortitude negates" resist="yes" dc="16" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Material" schooltext="Transmutation" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="Fortitude negates" resisttext="Yes" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>This spell causes instant growth of a humanoid creature, doubling its height and multiplying its weight by 8. This increase changes the creature's size category to the next larger one. The target gains a +2 size bonus to Strength, a -2 size penalty to Dexterity (to a minimum of 1), and a -1 penalty on attack rolls and AC due to its increased size. A humanoid creature whose size increases to Large has a space of 10 feet and a natural reach of 10 feet. This spell does not change the target's speed. If insufficient room is available for the desired growth, the creature attains the maximum possible size and may make a Strength check (using its increased Strength) to burst any enclosures in the process. If it fails, it is constrained without harm by the materials enclosing it - the spell cannot be used to crush a creature by increasing its size. All equipment worn or carried by a creature is similarly enlarged by the spell. Melee weapons affected by this spell deal more damage (see page 145). Other magical properties are not affected by this spell. Any enlarged item that leaves an enlarged creature's possession (including a projectile or thrown weapon) instantly returns to its normal size. This means that thrown and projectile weapons deal their normal damage. Magical properties of enlarged items are not increased by this spell. Multiple magical effects that increase size do not stack.

Enlarge person counters and dispels reduce person.

Enlarge person can be made permanent with a permanency spell.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Material</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Transmutation</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Evolution Surge, Lesser" level="2" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="touch" target="your eidolon" area="" effect="" duration="1 minute/level" save="DC 17 Will negates (harmless)" resist="no" dc="17" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Material" schooltext="Transmutation" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="Will negates" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>This spell causes your eidolon to take on new characteristics. You can grant the eidolon any evolution whose total cost does not exceed 2 evolution points. You may only grant one evolution with this spell, even if that evolution can be taken multiple times. You can grant an evolution that allows you to spend additional evolution points to upgrade that evolution. This spell cannot be used to grant an upgrade to an evolution that the eidolon already possesses. The eidolon must meet any prerequisites of the selected evolution. This spell does not allow an eidolon to exceed its maximum number of natural attacks.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Material</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Transmutation</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Guidance" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="touch" target="creature touched" area="" effect="" duration="1 minute or until discharged" save="Will negates (harmless)" resist="yes" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic" schooltext="Divination, Void Elemental" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="Harmless, Will negates" resisttext="Yes" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>This spell imbues the subject with a touch of divine guidance. The creature gets a +1 competence bonus on a single attack roll, saving throw, or skill check. It must choose to use the bonus before making the roll to which it applies.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Divination</spellschool>
					<spellschool>Void Elemental</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Invisibility" level="2" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="personal or touch" target="you or a creature or object weighing no more than 100 lbs./level" area="" effect="" duration="1 min./level (D)" save="Will negates (harmless) or Will negates (harmless, object)" resist="yes (harmless) or yes (harmless, object)" dc="17" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Material or Divine Focus" schooltext="Illusion, Void Elemental" subschooltext="Glamer" descriptortext="" savetext="Harmless, Object, Will negates" resisttext="Harmless, Object, Yes" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>The creature or object touched becomes invisible. If the recipient is a creature carrying gear, that vanishes, too. If you cast the spell on someone else, neither you nor your allies can see the subject, unless you can normally see invisible things or you employ magic to do so.

Items dropped or put down by an invisible creature become visible; items picked up disappear if tucked into the clothing or pouches worn by the creature. Light, however, never becomes invisible, although a source of light can become so (thus, the effect is that of a light with no visible source). Any part of an item that the subject carries but that extends more than 10 feet from it becomes visible.

Of course, the subject is not magically silenced, and certain other conditions can render the recipient detectable (such as swimming in water or stepping in a puddle). If a check is required, a stationary invisible creature has a +40 bonus on its Stealth checks. This bonus is reduced to +20 if the creature is moving. The spell ends if the subject attacks any creature. For purposes of this spell, an attack includes any spell targeting a foe or whose area or effect includes a foe. Exactly who is a foe depends on the invisible character's perceptions. Actions directed at unattended objects do not break the spell. Causing harm indirectly is not an attack. Thus, an invisible being can open doors, talk, eat, climb stairs, summon monsters and have them attack, cut the ropes holding a rope bridge while enemies are on the bridge, remotely trigger traps, open a portcullis to release attack dogs, and so forth. If the subject attacks directly, however, it immediately becomes visible along with all its gear. Spells such as bless that specifically affect allies but not foes are not attacks for this purpose, even when they include foes in their area.

Invisibility can be made permanent (on objects only) with a permanency spell.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Material or Divine Focus</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Illusion</spellschool>
					<spellschool>Void Elemental</spellschool>
					<spellsubschool>Glamer</spellsubschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Life Conduit" level="1" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="personal" target="you" area="" effect="" duration="1 round/level" save="" resist="" dc="16" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic" schooltext="Conjuration" subschooltext="Healing" descriptortext="" savetext="" resisttext="" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>You utilize life conduit to share hit points with your eidolon. While this spell is active, you can spend a swift action to transfer 1d6 hit points between you and your eidolon, either taking damage yourself and healing your eidolon or healing yourself and damaging your eidolon. If your eidolon moves farther than 50 feet from you, this spell ends.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Conjuration</spellschool>
					<spellsubschool>Healing</spellsubschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Light" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="touch" target="object touched" area="" effect="" duration="10 min./level" save="none" resist="no" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Material or Divine Focus" schooltext="Evocation, Wood Elemental" subschooltext="" descriptortext="Light" savetext="None" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>This spell causes a touched object to glow like a torch, shedding normal light in a 20-foot radius, and increasing the light level for an additional 20 feet by one step, up to normal light (darkness becomes dim light, and dim light becomes normal light). In an area of normal or bright light, this spell has no effect. The effect is immobile, but it can be cast on a movable object. You can only have one light spell active at any one time. If you cast this spell while another casting is still in effect, the previous casting is dispelled. If you make this spell permanent (through permanency or a similar effect), it does not count against this limit.

Light can be used to counter or dispel any darkness spell of equal or lower spell level.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Material or Divine Focus</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Evocation</spellschool>
					<spellschool>Wood Elemental</spellschool>
					<spelldescript>Light</spelldescript>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Mage Armor" level="1" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="touch" target="creature touched" area="" effect="" duration="1 hour/level (D)" save="Will negates (harmless)" resist="no" dc="16" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Focus" schooltext="Conjuration" subschooltext="Creation" descriptortext="Force" savetext="Harmless, Will negates" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>An invisible but tangible field of force surrounds the subject of a mage armor spell, providing a +4 armor bonus to AC. Unlike mundane armor, mage armor entails no armor check penalty, arcane spell failure chance, or speed reduction. Since mage armor is made of force, incorporeal creatures can't bypass it the way they do normal armor.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Focus</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Conjuration</spellschool>
					<spellsubschool>Creation</spellsubschool>
					<spelldescript>Force</spelldescript>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Mage Hand" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="close (25 + 5 ft./2 levels)" target="one nonmagical, unattended object weighing up to 5 lbs." area="" effect="" duration="concentration" save="none" resist="no" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic" schooltext="Transmutation" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="None" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>You point your finger at an object and can lift it and move it at will from a distance. As a move action, you can propel the object as far as 15 feet in any direction, though the spell ends if the distance between you and the object ever exceeds the spell's range.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Transmutation</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Message" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="medium (100 + 10 ft./level)" target="one creature/level" area="" effect="" duration="10 min./level" save="none" resist="no" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Focus" schooltext="Transmutation, Air Elemental" subschooltext="" descriptortext="Language-Dependent" savetext="None" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>You can whisper messages and receive whispered replies. Those nearby can hear these messages with a DC 25 Perception check. You point your finger at each creature you want to receive the message. When you whisper, the whispered message is audible to all targeted creatures within range. Magical silence, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal (or a thin sheet of lead), or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks the spell. The message does not have to travel in a straight line. It can circumvent a barrier if there is an open path between you and the subject, and the path's entire length lies within the spell's range. The creatures that receive the message can whisper a reply that you hear. The spell transmits sound, not meaning; it doesn't transcend language barriers. To speak a message, you must mouth the words and whisper.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Focus</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Transmutation</spellschool>
					<spellschool>Air Elemental</spellschool>
					<spelldescript>Language-Dependent</spelldescript>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Read Magic" level="0" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="personal" target="you" area="" effect="" duration="10 min./level" save="" resist="" dc="15" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Focus" schooltext="Divination" subschooltext="" descriptortext="" savetext="" resisttext="" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>You can decipher magical inscriptions on objects - books, scrolls, weapons, and the like - that would otherwise be unintelligible. This deciphering does not normally invoke the magic contained in the writing, although it may do so in the case of a cursed or trapped scroll. Furthermore, once the spell is cast and you have read the magical inscription, you are thereafter able to read that particular writing without recourse to the use of read magic. You can read at the rate of one page (250 words) per minute. The spell allows you to identify a glyph of warding with a DC 13 Spellcraft check, a greater glyph of warding with a DC 16 Spellcraft check, or any symbol spell with a Spellcraft check (DC 10 + spell level).

Read magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Focus</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Divination</spellschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Rejuvenate Eidolon, Lesser" level="1" class="Summoner" casttime="1 action" range="touch" target="eidolon touched" area="" effect="" duration="instantaneous" save="none" resist="no" dc="16" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic, Material" schooltext="Conjuration" subschooltext="Healing" descriptortext="" savetext="None" resisttext="No" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>By laying your hand upon an eidolon, you cause its wounds to close and its form to solidify. This spell cures 1d10 points of damage +1 point per caster level (maximum +5).</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Material</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Conjuration</spellschool>
					<spellsubschool>Healing</spellsubschool>
				</spell>
				<spell name="Restore Eidolon, Lesser" level="2" class="Summoner" casttime="3 rounds" range="touch" target="eidolon touched" area="" effect="" duration="instantaneous" save="DC 17 Will negates (harmless)" resist="yes (harmless)" dc="17" casterlevel="5" componenttext="Verbal, Somatic" schooltext="Conjuration" subschooltext="Healing" descriptortext="" savetext="Will negates" resisttext="Yes" spontaneous="yes">
					<description>This spell functions as lesser restoration, except it only affects an eidolon.</description>
					<spellcomp>Verbal</spellcomp>
					<spellcomp>Somatic</spellcomp>
					<spellschool>Conjuration</spellschool>
					<spellsubschool>Healing</spellsubschool>
				</spell>
			</spellsknown>
			<spellsmemorized/>
			<spellbook/>
			<spellclasses>
				<spellclass name="Summoner (Synthesist)" maxspelllevel="2" spells="Spontaneous">
					<spelllevel level="0" unlimited="yes" used="0"/>
					<spelllevel level="1" maxcasts="6" used="0"/>
					<spelllevel level="2" maxcasts="3" used="0"/>
				</spellclass>
			</spellclasses>
			<journals>
				<journal name="Title" gamedate="0" realdate="20180430" xp="0" pp="0" gp="0" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" prestigeaward="0" prestigespend="0">
					<description/>
				</journal>
				<journal name="Title" gamedate="0" realdate="20180430" xp="0" pp="0" gp="0" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" prestigeaward="0" prestigespend="0">
					<description/>
				</journal>
				<journal name="Title" gamedate="0" realdate="20180430" xp="0" pp="0" gp="0" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" prestigeaward="0" prestigespend="0">
					<description/>
				</journal>
				<journal name="Title" gamedate="0" realdate="20180430" xp="0" pp="0" gp="0" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" prestigeaward="0" prestigespend="0">
					<description/>
				</journal>
				<journal name="Title" gamedate="0" realdate="20180430" xp="0" pp="0" gp="0" sp="0" cp="0" cn1="0" cn2="0" cn3="0" cn4="0" prestigeaward="0" prestigespend="0">
					<description/>
				</journal>
			</journals>
			<images>
				<image filename="Mark-image001.jpg"/>
			</images>
			<validation>
				<report/>
			</validation>
			<settings summary="Advanced Class Guide: Advanced Class Guide; Advanced Player's Guide: Advanced Player's Guide, Advanced Player's Guide Familiars, Advanced Player's Guide Traits, Advanced Player's Guide New Combat Maneuvers; Advanced Race Guide: Advanced Race Guide, Race Builder; Adventurer's Guide: Adventurer's Guide; Book of the Damned: Book of the Damned; Occult Adventures: Occult Adventures; Ultimate Campaign -&gt; Ultimate Campaign Character Backgrounds: Unrestricted Traits &amp; Drawbacks; Ultimate Combat: Ultimate Combat; Ultimate Equipment: Ultimate Equipment; Ultimate Intrigue: Ultimate Intrigue; Ultimate Magic: Ultimate Magic, Ultimate Magic Familiars; Bestiary: Bestiary Familiars, Bestiary Free Content; Player Companion: Adventurer's Armory; Campaign Setting: Andoran, Birthplace of Freedom, Belkzen, Hold of the Orc Lords, Inner Sea World Guide, Lost Treasures, Ships of the Inner Sea, Tombs of Golarion, Undead Unleashed; Miscellaneous Content: Character Traits Web Enhancement, Core Rulebook Deities, GameMastery Guide, Paizo Blog; Pathfinder Modules: Daughters of Fury, Doom Comes to Dustpawn, Fangwood Keep, Murder's Mark, No Response from Deepmar, Plunder and Peril, Tears at Bitter Manor, The Dragon's Demand, The Emerald Spire, The Harrowing, The Midnight Mirror; Pathfinder Adventure Paths: Carrion Crown, Council of Thieves, Curse of the Crimson Throne, Giantslayer, Hell's Rebels, Hell's Vengeance, Iron Gods, Ironfang Invasion, Jade Regent, Kingmaker, Mummy's Mask, Reign of Winter, Rise of the Runelords Anniversary Edition, Ruins of Azlant, Serpent's Skull, Shattered Star, Skull &amp; Shackles, Strange Aeons, War for the Crown, Wrath of the Righteous; Advancement Speed: Medium Advancement; Firearm Availability: Emerging Guns; Experimental Options: Don't show statblock summary window; Output Options: Hide Ammo (in weapons), Hide Unusable Skills, Hide Validation Messages, Show Activated Abilities &amp; Adjustments, Show Hero Portrait, Show Sourcebook Report"/>
			<minions/>
		</character>
	</public>
</document>